只有一种生物为了自己的生存
Only one creature has carved a life for itself
在地球的每一个角落都留下了印迹
in every habitat on earth.
那就是人类
That creature is us.
天地悠悠
All over the world,
我们仍依靠创造力来努力存活于世
we still use our ingenuity to survive in the wild places,
远离文明开化的城市
far from the city lights,
直面原始险恶的自然
face to face with raw nature.
海洋覆盖了地球表面的70%
The sea covers 70% of our planet's surface.
四分之三的地球生物以海洋为家
It's home to three-quarters of all life on Earth.
所有徜徉其中的生物
All the creatures found here are perfectly adapted
都在这里生息繁衍
to thrive in the ocean...
只有一个例外
..all except one.
我们并非为水而生
We are not evolved for a life aquatic...
这个危险陌生的环境
..and we're way out of our depth
超乎了我们的极限
in this dangerous and alien world.
但是对于那些敢于探险的人们来说
But great opportunities await those people
巨大的机遇就在前方
who dare to venture into the water.
我们一步步向海洋的深处进发
As we immerse ourselves ever deeper in the big blue,
如何克服面对的这些巨大挑战呢
how do we overcome the enormous challenges that confront us?
海洋
深入蔚蓝世界
人类和海洋的联系始于海岸线
Our relationship with the ocean begins on the coast.
即使在这里  海洋的力量也不容小觑
Even here, the sea is a force to be reckoned with.
西班牙北部的加利西亚地区
Galicia, in Northern Spain,
绵延着欧洲最为凶险的海岸线之一
is home to one of Europe's most treacherous coasts.
但如果你像哈维尔和安格尔一样愿意冒险
But the more extreme the conditions, the greater the rewards,
那么环境越是恶劣
if, like Javier and Angel,
回报就越是丰厚
you're prepared to take the risk.
我的老天...
相当有挑战啊
兄弟你要是先走一步...
你先来吧...
你先来...
哈维尔和安格尔两人来捕获一种奇特生物
Javier and Angel are on the hunt for a strange creature
它们附着在被海浪拍打的岩石表面
that clings to the wave-battered rocks...
位于这些悬崖峭壁的最深处
at the bottom of these cliffs.
他们行动要快
They have to move fast.
他们的猎物只会在潮退时显露出来
Their quarry is only exposed at low tide.
加油啊
Vamos! Arriba! Arriba!
小心
好了...
现在下手
他们想捕获的叫鹅藤壶
It's goose barnacles they're after,
一千克能卖到200欧价格的珍稀海味
a highly prized delicacy that can sell for 200 euros a kilo.
但是捕获却极其困难
But it's not easy pickings.
每年都有五名左右的捕获者为此丧命
Each year, about five collectors die.
如此艰险的工作鲜有人问津
Few dare work when it's this rough.
但那些真正的勇士可以靠此赚个盆满钵满
But those who do can charge a premium for their harvest.
小心这个浪头...
在海浪的猛击下  哈维尔满载而归
Despite the onslaught, Javier's filled his bag.
现在该安格尔了
Now it's Angel's turn,
尽管海浪愈发汹涌
and though it's getting even rougher...
他还是去了  并且没系安全绳
..he's going in with no safety rope.
不系绳子可以让他穿梭于海浪之中
Working unattached allows him to dash between waves
抵达最低的一些岩石
and reach the lowest rocks,
那里的鹅藤壶个头也最大
where the biggest barnacles grow.
但是稍微一滑就是致命的
But one slip could be fatal.
尽管海浪又一次袭来
Although the tide's coming in,
安格尔却没打算收手
Angel's determined to collect more.
哈维尔和安格尔的赌博得到了回报
Javier and Angel's gamble paid off.
短短两小时  他们捕获的鹅藤壶
In two hours, they've gathered enough goose barnacles
足够让他们进账800欧了
to fetch around 800 euros.
收成不错的一天
Not bad for a day at the seaside.
你得用绳子
要捕这么大个的
没错...
把自己吊起来
正是这些丰富的物产诱使我们一次次的冒险
It's this abundance of food that entices us into the waves.
但是海岸线再向外延伸一点的地方
And just a little further out,
有着更多的宝藏
there are even greater riches.
大陆架水域只占世界海洋面积的十分之一
Coastal waters account for just one-tenth of the world's oceans,
但它们却孕育着大量丰富的海洋物种
but they're home to the vast majority of marine life.
问题在于  探险的地方离开海岸越远
The trouble is, as we venture further from the shore,
危险系数就越高
the dangers escalate.
本杰明努力成为一名捕鲸能手
Benjamin's training to be a harpoonist
他深知  总有一天
and he knows, any day now,
学到的东西将面临真刀真枪的考验
all he's learned could be put to the test.
出海捕鲸之前...
我们都十分紧张...
...但如果不去
就没有食物
他住在印度尼西亚一个叫兰伯塔的小岛上
He lives on a small Indonesian island called Lembata.
这片土地很贫瘠  很难生长作物
Few crops grow in this rocky land,
就连活下来都是一个巨大的挑战
and even surviving from the sea is a struggle.
但是他们等待着一种动物的出现
But there's one animal they wait for
它们能让村民们一夜致富
that can dramatically change their fortunes.
鲸鱼  鲸鱼
全村上下迅速行动起来
The whole village springs into action.
他们要抓紧时间出海
It's a race against time to get out to sea.
本杰明和他的乡亲们要捕获的
Benjamin and the rest of the crew
是有史以来最大的食肉动物
are about to take on the biggest predator that's ever lived.
鲸鱼的尾部和头部
强健有力...
...能使我们全都
死翘翘
他们都很清楚面临的危险
They all know the risks,
但是如此这般的好机会  失不再来
but opportunities don't come much bigger than this.
抹香鲸
The sperm whale.
身长可达18米
Up to 18 metres long,
这些无敌的海中巨物威猛无比
these mighty leviathans are powerful animals
它们绝不会束手就擒
and they won't go down without a fight.
只凭借简陋的小木筏和手工捕鱼器
With simple wooden boats and handmade weapons,
村民们看起来没什么胜算
the whalers seem ill-prepared for battle,
但是六百多年来一直都是这样过来的
but this is how it's been for 600 years.
只有当鲸浮上来呼吸的时候他们才有机会
They can only harpoon the whale when it surfaces to breathe...
因此动作必须要快
..so they need to move fast.
本杰明表哥准备向抹香鲸发出舍身一击
Benjamin's brother prepares to launch himself at the whale.
这是整个过程最危险的一步
This is the most dangerous moment of all.
但他失手了
But he misses...
现在趁它潜下去之前必须有勇士挺身而出
..and now someone else must step up before the whale dives.
本杰明大显身手的时候到了
Benjamin's moment has arrived.
他成功了
He's got it.
但是斗争才刚刚开始
But the battle has just begun.
这条抹香鲸开始挣扎反抗
As the whale fights to break free,
村民们调整位置  想再次戳中它
they move to harpoon it again.
他们必须防止它潜下  从底部攻击船只
They need to prevent it from diving and pulling a boat under.
但这些还不够
But it's not enough.
村民们忌惮它强有力的尾巴
Terrified of the thrashing whale,
于是聚在了一起
the crew scramble to safety.
另一条船加入了捕获抹香鲸的战斗
Another boat attacks and harpoons the whale once more.
同时拖拉好几条船
Now dragging several boats,
这条鲸慢慢泄气了
the whale slowly tires.
终于  它无力反抗
Eventually, its struggles are exhausted
他们对着它的后背骨来了最后一击
and a final cut, through its backbone, is made.
在这次历经八小时的史诗般的鏖战中
It's been an epic eight-hour battle,
本杰明表现出了他的技艺和勇气
but Benjamin has shown his skill and bravery...
这次捕猎没有人员伤亡
..and this time everyone returns safely home.
一条鲸的死亡也许会让我们潸然泪下
The death of a whale may be sad to us,
但这是村民们赖以生存的命根
but this is their lifeline.
一次捕杀可以提供整个村子几个月的食物
One catch can feed a village for months,
而这种在兰伯塔岛上进行的小规模捕猎
and this small-scale hunt in Lembata
不会影响到海洋里的鲸鱼数量
doesn't threaten whale numbers in these oceans.
他们一年大概只捕获6条左右
They only take around six whales a year.
抹香鲸浑身都是宝
Nothing is wasted.
家家户户都能分到一份肉
The meat is shared out.
作为完成致命一击的勇士
As the man who dealt the decisive blow,
本杰明得到的那份更多一些
Benjamin gets a larger share.
至少一段时间内  他的家人不会受饿
And for a while at least, his family won't be going hungry.
尽管我们进化成为了适合陆地生存的物种
Although we've evolved for a life on land,
我们却成为了颇有效率的海洋猎手
we've become remarkably efficient oceanic hunters.
良好的适应性引领着人类
Adaptability is the secret of our success
在探索海洋的过程中不断迸发新的灵感
at discovering new ways to exploit the ocean.
在一些特别的地区
And in a few special places,
这意味着借助海洋生物的帮忙
this means working with the creatures of the sea.
巴西拉瓜那地区的渔民们
These fishermen of Laguna in Brazil
在人类和野生动物之间建立了一种
have forged one of the most extraordinary partnerships
整个地球独一无二的合作伙伴关系
between humans and wild animals found anywhere on Earth.
爱德生起了个大早去捕捞
Edson is up early to fish
每年五月都溯游经过此地的大批鲻鱼
the large numbers of mullet that migrate through these waters every May.
但是有一个麻烦
But there's a problem.
海水很浑浊
The water's so murky
渔民们拿不准应该在何处撒网
the fishermen can't see where to cast their nets.
所以他们与海洋中最聪明的动物携手
So they join forces with the most intelligent animal in the sea.
然而  正如人际交往中的一样
But, like all relationships,
心急吃不了热豆腐
a certain amount of patience is required.
终于  他们的帮手浮出了海面
Finally, their friends surface.
当地的瓶鼻海豚在拉瓜那地区可是大名鼎鼎
The local bottlenose dolphins are celebrities in Laguna.
事实上是  爱德生和他伙伴艾尔弗雷多
In fact, Edson and his pal Alfredo
能够叫出每一只的名字
know each one by name.
费格雷多 会帮我们
逮到大批大批的鱼...
...那是 斯库布
没错  是他
难以置信的是
Incredibly,
海豚们把鲻鱼往渔民们处赶
the dolphins drive the mullet towards the fishermen,
甚至还会通过这些独特的潜水动作
and even signal when to cast their nets,
发出撒网的信号
with these distinctive dives.
渔民说  他们可以通过
The fishermen say they can tell the size of the school,
海豚下潜的力量与方向
and which way it's travelling
分辨出鱼群的规模和游动的方向
from the vigour and direction of the dive.
海豚完成了捕鱼过程中最难的部分
The dolphins do the hard work herding the mullet.
鱼儿成了渔民的盘中餐
The fish are served to the fishermen on a plate...
可是海豚能获得什么呢  人们却不清楚
...but what the dolphins stand to gain is less clear.
既然它们可以通过回声侦测到猎物
Since they detect prey by echolocation,
那肯定能在浑浊的水里捕猎
they have no problem hunting in the murky water,
但是从整个鱼群中捕捉个体十分困难
but picking off individuals from the school is more difficult.
渔网似乎使鱼儿惊慌失措而四散逃窜
It seems the nets panic the fish into breaking formation,
对于海豚来说也更容易追捕到食物
making them much easier for the dolphins to chase down.
随着渔网一点点收紧
As the nets are hauled in,
团队合作的好处便显现出来
the benefits of teamwork are revealed.
埃德森和其他渔民很清楚
Edson and the other fishermen have no doubt
海豚帮了他们多大的忙
how much the dolphins help them.
今天海豚表现
真不错...
有十三多公斤
一次撒网就捕到八十多条鲻鱼
无论我们如何获取海产品
No matter how we catch it,
它们对人类的生存都至关重要
seafood is vital to human survival,
世界一半人口的蛋白质供应
providing the main source of protein
都来自海产品
for about half the world's population.
我们与大海长久以来的紧密联系
But there's a lot more to our ancient connection
远远不止食物这么简单
with the sea than just food.
我们越是依赖海洋
The more we've come to depend on the ocean,
越是开拓海洋广阔的边疆
and the further we've pushed into its vast frontier,
它对我们生活的影响也就越明显
the greater its influence has become in our lives.
太平洋覆盖了地球三分之一的面积
The Pacific covers one-third of the globe.
大洋正中的一丛零星小岛
The tiny specks of land in the middle of it
大概是人类所能抵达之极
are about as remote as life can get for a human being.
海岛的陆地如此之少
With so few options on land,
使得周围的海域几乎支撑起了
the surrounding ocean underpins almost
太平洋上生命的方方面面
every aspect of life on a Pacific island.
在距离大陆超过三千平方米的海域上
Over 3,000 kilometres from the nearest continent,
夏威夷是最为偏远的海岛之一
Hawaii is one of the most isolated of all.
海洋对人类生存的影响
There are few places where the sea has had
在这里体现得淋漓尽致  无处可比
a greater impact on human existence.
大海对我们意义深远  它就是我们的家园
The ocean, significantly to us, it's our home.
我们的联系如此紧密
Our connection is so great,
我们视她为生命的源头
we look at it as our origin.
水即我们  我们即水
The water is who we are,
她是我们的生身父母
and the water is our mother, our father,
是我们的神明
our gods.
对土生土长的夏威夷人来说
For Tom "Pohako" Stone,
在海洋中尽情地展示技术
displaying his skill in the ocean
是他们最重要的能力
is a central part of what it means to be Hawaiian.
在碧波中逐流
Sliding on waves, as it was known,
是波利尼亚人几千年来的传统
has been practised by the Polynesians for millennia.
但那毕竟是一千年前
But it was around 1,000 years ago,
他们来到了夏威夷之后
when they arrived in Hawaii,
这项传统变逐渐演化成了冲浪
that it evolved into surfing.
当我们真正
When we actually learned t
学会了制作滑板
hat we could construct boards
站立起来冲浪
to stand up and surf a wave,
它便成为了我们文化中
it became a very ritualistic
根深蒂固的一部分
component of our culture.
对于居住在夏威夷的祖先而言
Far more than just a sport,
冲浪不仅是一项运动
surfing was a sacred art form
更是一门神圣的艺术
for Tom's ancestors.
这是他们社会的核心内容
It was a core part of their society,
是勇士  国王  王后
and the noble pursuit
才配追求的崇高目标
of warriors, kings and queens.
女性冲浪在我们这里历史悠久
We have a lot of history about women that...that surf,
她们的技术非常高超
and, you know, they surfed so well
达到了神一般的境界
that they actually reached godly status.
我们很尊敬这些女性
We revered these women.
有着古老起源的冲浪
From ancient origins,
现如今已风靡全球
surfing has now gone global.
对有些人而言  追逐自己的生命之旅
And for some, searching for the ride of your life
已经成为一种执着的迷恋
has become an extreme obsession.
2009年12月9日
December 9th, 2009.
全世界的冲浪精英齐聚于夏威夷
The world's surfing elite has gathered in Hawaii
踏上十年来最高的浪尖
to ride some of the biggest swells
在海滨边尽情戏耍
to hit these shores in over a decade.
冲浪本身已发生了许多变化
Surfing's certainly changed,
但对很多人来说  它依旧是一种生活方式
but for many it's still a way of life
最棒的冲浪骑手依旧被奉为
and the best riders are still revered as gods
世界范围内冲浪人的神人
amongst the worldwide surfing tribe.
巨浪高达15米  有5层楼的高度
With waves over 15 metres, five storeys high,
这是技巧和耐力的真正考验
this is a real test of skill and stamina.
肯・布拉德肖因能驾驭26米高的海浪而闻名
Ken Bradshaw is famed for taming a 26-metre wave,
这可能是目前的最高纪录
probably the biggest ever ridden.
但是这些无法预知的浪潮
But these unpredictable swells
仍有可能夺去最有经验的冲浪者的性命
can claim even the most seasoned surfer.
陷入这样一座翻滚的浪山中
Trapped in a rolling mountain of white water,
肯就像洗衣机里的洋娃娃一般翻滚不止
Ken is tossed around like a rag doll in a washing machine.
他刚浮出水面
Just as he surfaces,
又是一波巨浪呼啸而来
another giant breaker comes crashing in.
在六波海浪连续无情的冲击之后
After a relentless pounding from six successive waves,
肯终于安全逃了出来
Ken eventually escapes in one piece.
所有的巨浪爱好者都知道有风险
All big wave surfers know the risks,
但肾上腺素和荣耀却是致瘾的
but the adrenaline and the glory is addictive.
正如古老的夏威夷人发现的那样
And just as the ancient Hawaiians discovered,
冲浪依旧是对人类
surfing is still the most
征服海洋这一能力的最壮丽的诠释
spectacular demonstration of our ability to conquer the waves.
我们对大海的驾驭令人惊叹
Our mastery of the sea is impressive,
但它的狂暴永远无法被我们驯服
but we'll never tame its full fury.
12月9日这天的滔天巨浪
The enormous waves of December 9th
是太平洋强大的
were created by intense
热带气旋活动一手创造的
tropical cyclone activity in the Pacific.
当暖流为海洋上空
When warm waters fuel
低气压推波助澜
the ferocity of depressions over the ocean,
它们便会联手创造地球上最为恶劣的环境
they can create the most violent weather systems on Earth.
在狂风暴雨的时节
People must stay well away from the raging sea
人们一定要远离凶猛的大海
during these tempestuous times,
但他们却无法抑制内心的渴望
but they can't stop it coming to them.
这些时速达到
These super-storms,
300公里的超级风暴
with winds of over 300 kilometres per hour,
肆虐人类世界
wreak havoc on the human world.
从重创中恢复过来可能要数十年
It can take years to recover from the destruction.
有时  那些半径超过1600公里的飓风和台风
Sometimes over 1,600 kilometres wide,
是海洋那可敬又可畏的力量
hurricanes and typhoons are persistent reminders
最好的见证
of the ocean's awesome force.
无怪乎沿海居民
It's little wonder that coastal people
对于这非凡的水域
look at these mighty waters
怀有最崇高的敬意
with great reverence...
但这不仅仅是因为海洋强大的力量
...but not just for the power of the ocean,
还有水里居住的生物们
but also the power of the creatures that live in it.
在离巴布新几内亚不远的群岛上
In the islands off Papua New Guinea,
布莱斯被认为是海洋巫师
Blais is known as a sorcerer of the sea.
他是仅剩的几个
Possessing the mysterious ability
拥有神秘的召唤深海鲨鱼能力的
to summon sharks from the deep,
鲨鱼召唤者之一
he's one of the last so-called shark callers,
这是一种披上了迷信色彩的传统狩猎技术
a traditional hunting technique steeped in superstition.
鲨鱼在我们的世界里是极受尊敬的生物
我们会向鲨鱼的灵魂歌唱...
祈求它允许我们捕捉它
布莱斯很尊敬宗教礼仪
Blais respects ritual,
但他同样知晓鲨鱼的习性
but he also understands shark behaviour.
在水里拨弄出咔嗒的声音
Rattling in the water
可以模仿喂鱼的行为
mimics the activity of feeding fish.
鲨鱼可以从三公里外
Sharks can detect these vibrations
就探测到这种振动
from three kilometres away,
但它们不一定会响应
but they don't always respond.
真正的鲨鱼召唤者有
足够的耐心...
...忍受数小时的
等待
由于捕鱼业重挫了鲨鱼数量
And as industrial fishing decimates shark numbers,
等待也愈加长久
the waits are getting even longer.
终于  一条灰色的礁鲨从深海中现身了
Finally, a grey reef shark emerges from the blue.
布莱斯抚慰了它的灵魂
Blais has appeased its spirit.
但现在  他必须抓住它
But now he has to catch it,
而鲨鱼又是出了名的反复无常
and sharks are notoriously skittish.
这是一个猫捉老鼠的游戏
It's a game of cat and mouse.
布莱斯试图将鲨鱼引诱到身边
Blais tries to entice the shark
套一圈绳索在它项上
close enough to slip a noose around its neck...
可只要一步走错  满盘皆输
...but one false move and it's game over.
最终鲨鱼上钩了
Finally it takes the bait.
他耐心准备着套索
Slowly he prepares the noose.
布莱斯无法把持住不停扭动的鲨鱼
Blais can't keep hold of the thrashing shark,
但这个木浮却可以防止鲨鱼潜入水中
but this wooden float prevents it diving.
随后  就像中了咒语一般
Then, as if under a spell,
鲨鱼突然静止不动了
the shark suddenly stops.
事实上是木浮利用了鲨鱼生理上的特点
But in fact the float exploits a quirk in shark biology,
使它精疲力尽
exhausting it so much,
进入了紧张性僵直的状态
it enters a state known as tonic immobility.
布莱斯小心翼翼地接近鲨鱼
Blais approaches with caution.
此时的鲨鱼还有很强的生命力
The shark is still very much alive
它的撕咬仍能造成致命的伤害
and its bite could cause serious injury.
以往  布莱斯会杀了鲨鱼作为食物
In the past, Blais would have killed the shark for food.
但今天他放了它
But today he lets it go free.
布莱斯致力于
Blais is committed to
保护召唤鲨鱼的文化
keeping his shark-calling culture alive...
这也意味着要挽救鲨鱼的生命
...and this means keeping sharks alive.
现在鲨鱼数量
急剧减少
我很担心...
...我们的子孙后代
没有鲨鱼
我们的生活也会随之消亡
其实不仅仅是传统文化正饱受威胁
And it's not just traditions that are threatened.
在很多海域
In some seas around the world,
鱼类数量的持续下降
a growing shortage of fish
迫使人们越潜越深
is forcing people deeper and deeper,
只为一次可观的打捞
just to land a decent catch.
深到他们不得不冒险挑战人类极限
So deep, they venture to the very limits of human survival.
欢迎来到帕阿林潜水者的世界
Welcome to the world of the Pa-aling divers,
这也许是最危险的捕鱼方式
perhaps the most dangerous fishing method of all.
这八十个人里  大部分都是少年
80 men, many of whom are still teenagers,
他们准备好了要潜至40多米之深
are preparing to dive to over 40 metres,
通过这简陋的空气管将就着呼吸
breathing air pumped through these makeshift tubes
那生锈的空气压缩机压出的空气
by this rusty compressor.
约瑟芬是最年轻出海人之一
Joseph is one of the youngest aboard,
但他却很清楚可能的危险
but he's aware of the risks.
用压缩机潜水
是很危险的
他目睹过这份工作中存在着的致命危险
He's already witnessed just how lethal his job can be.
我一个很亲密的
伙伴死了...
我们试图抢救他  但失败了
他说想
休息一会...
没想到却是
永别
菲律宾海域曾海产丰富
The seas around the Philippines were once rich with life,
但由于过度开发
but they've been so over-exploited
要获得丰收就要下潜到危险的深度
that decent fish numbers are only found at perilous depths.
渔网聚成了一个巨大的球体
The divers guide the huge ball of nets
由潜水员带至40米深处的海床
40 metres down to the sea floor,
但他们的氧气供给始终存在着危险
but all the while their air supply is at risk.
回到船上
Back on the boat,
破烂的压缩机和每况愈下的空气管
the ailing compressor and the ever-worsening tangle of tubes
需要随时监控
need constant attention.
正如衰弱的心脏给阻塞的动脉泵血一般
Like a failing heart pumping through clogged arteries,
如果循环系统受阻
if this circulation system fails,
潜至如此深度  就几乎意味着死亡
at this depth, it's almost certain death.
约瑟芬和队友解开了渔网
Joseph and the team unravel the nets
并将它们系牢在石头上
and lay them out by securing them to rocks.
他们必须速战速决
They must work fast.
约瑟芬清楚  在如此深度待得越久
Joseph knows, the longer he spends at these depths,
处境就越危险
the more dangerous it becomes.
每呼吸一次  就会有更多氮气进入体内
With every breath, more nitrogen dissolves in his body,
使身体更易受到减压病的侵害
making him increasingly vulnerable to decompression sickness
即潜水病
"the bends".
网的顶端悬浮着注满空气的塑料容器
The top of the net is suspended by plastic containers filled with air,
在下方形成了一个巨大的孔状陷阱
creating a huge cavernous trap beneath.
现在该布下惊吓线了
Now it's time to set the scare line.
船拖着长达千米的惊吓线
The boats drag the 1,000-metre line
围着网布成了一个巨大的圈
to form a huge circle around the net,
潜水者则沿着线分布
and the divers position themselves along it.
约瑟芬和队友们向渔网游去
Joseph and the team begin closing the trap
开始收紧陷阱
by swimming towards the net.
涌动的水流和上升的水帘
The waving streamers and the curtain of rising bubbles
惊散了鱼儿
panics the fish and they flee.
随着潜水者们逐步将线收紧
As the line of divers tightens,
越来越多的鱼向上游入了张开的渔网
more and more fish swim straight into the gaping net.
这种深海围鱼法十分有效
This deep-sea round-up is so effective,
能捕到礁带范围内的半数鱼儿
it can take 50% of the fish from a reef.
网已经收了
The net is closed,
现在约瑟芬要去做一件更危险的事
and now Joseph must do something even more dangerous,
进入网中将鱼们赶入网的深处
get inside and herd the catch to the far end.
如果你在网中
失去氧气供给或被缠住了...
...你肯定就
死那儿了
船上  互相缠绕的空气管情况更糟了
On deck, the tangled web of tubes is getting worse.
一旦集中了鱼群
Once the catch is concentrated,
他们就会将网从固定点松开
the net is released from its anchor points.
现在到了最危险的步骤
Now comes the most lethal stage of all-
牵着网浮至水面
guiding the net as it shoots to the surface.
经常有潜水员因上升太快而得了潜水病
All too often, the divers ascend too quickly and get the bends.
战利品已成功拉上船  成果也可见一斑
As the catch is hauled onto the boat, its size is revealed.
一吨左右的鱼量不算太差
Just under a tonne of fish isn't bad
但离几年前的收成还差得远
but it's nowhere near what these fishermen were landing a few years ago.
而且这不是唯一的问题
And this isn't the only problem.
有些队员已经患上了潜水病
Some of the crew do have the bends.
一名潜水员不得不回到海底以缓解症状
One diver has returned to the bottom to relieve the symptoms,
同时  离水面更近的地方  另一名
whilst, closer to the surface, another is
正接受按摩以缓解脊梁上作痛的水泡
massaged to release the painful bubbles in his spine.
每天  这些潜水员们
Every day, these Pa-aling divers
都为日益变少的回报承受着剧增的风险
are taking greater risks for dwindling rewards.
我也许能找些别的工作...
...安全的工作
...不会伤害
身体的工作
约瑟芬有一个梦想
Joseph has his dreams,
但是现实是残酷的
but the harsh reality is
为了糊口他今天必须再下潜两次
he'll be diving twice again today just to make ends meet.
我们在海洋上取得了巨大成功
We've become so successful in the ocean
曾有人预言在五十年内
it's predicted that in 50 years
所有的鱼将消失殆尽
almost all the fish could be gone...
而这可能并不是唯一的变数
..and this may not be the only change to come.
全世界的海平面都在上升
All around the world, sea levels are rising.
用不了多久海洋将成为我们星球的主宰
Soon our planet could be even more dominated by the ocean,
我们在地球上的求生之道
and our ability to survive here
也将被逼至极限
will be pushed to the very limit.
但有些人
Yet there are some people
已经适应了水上的生活
who've already adapted to life in a water world.
在婆罗洲  苏拉威西岛与菲律宾之间的珊瑚海中
In the coral seas between Borneo, Sulawesi and the Philippines,
有些人的生存方式
there are people who live more intimately with the ocean
比世上任何一个种群更亲近海洋
than any other culture on earth.
巴乔村的人居住在海面上
The Bajau Laut build their lives in the middle of the sea,
而且通常离海岸有数公里的距离
often many kilometres from land.
海洋对他们生活的方方面面
The ocean has a profound influence
都有着深远的影响
on every aspect of their existence.
他们甚至通过潮汐的节奏
They even measure the passage of time
来得知时间的流逝
by the rhythm of the tides
而不是传统的分分秒秒
rather than minutes and hours.
还有一些人与海洋的渊源则更深
And there are some whose relationship with the sea runs even deeper.
住在船屋上的巴乔村民们
The Bajau, who live on houseboats,
则完全切断了他们与陆地的联系
have almost completely severed their ties with the land.
诺哈拉很少踏上陆地
Nohara rarely sets foot ashore.
我在船上出生...
一生都在海上
我喜欢船上的生活...
因为这样我们
想去哪儿就去哪儿
我们可以远航觅食...
也可以远离烦恼
诺哈拉一家通常只有在买粮食燃料
Nohara and her family usually only visit land
或船需要维修时
to trade for rice and fuel,
才会踏上陆地
or to mend their boats.
但像很多巴乔人一样  诺哈拉"晕陆"
But, like many Bajau, Nohara gets "land-sick"
因此她宁愿待在船上
and she prefers to stay aboard.
她的家庭没有国籍
Her family has no nationality,
没有固定的停留之处  也几乎一穷二白
no fixed abode and almost no money,
但海洋给了他们所需的一切
but the ocean provides everything they need.
他们可以食用一系列让人眼花缭乱的海产
They eat a bewildering variety of seafood.
她的孩子们很小就适应了水上的生活
Her children adapt to an aquatic way of life from a very young age.
一些巴乔的孩子们经常待在海里
Some Bajau children spend so much time in the sea,
他们的眼睛更适应水下视物
their eyes adjust to focus better underwater.
但这个群体中有名成员
But there's one member of this community
他的适应力令人称奇
whose adaptation is even more staggering.
瑟宾是一名水下猎人
Sulbin is an underwater hunter,
他是人类能在水下生存之极限
and the living proof of just how far we can push our bodies
活生生的例子
towards a life aquatic.
我潜水时
感觉很放松...
下了海里就像回了家...
感觉和在陆地上差不多
瑟宾在为晚餐寻找食物
Sulbin's search for supper
他开始了一段穿梭于海浪尖的神奇之旅
takes him on an incredible journey under the waves,
他的能力绝对会让你目瞪口呆
and his abilities will take your breath away.
他以近乎神游的状态开始准备
First he prepares by entering a trance-like state.
下水之前
我必须将心思集中在呼吸上
我只在完全放松的情况下潜水
瑟宾即将让身体
Sulbin is about to push his body
超越极限
almost beyond the realms of possibility,
如果你想和他一起试试
and if you want to try and join him,
那就准备屏住呼吸  越久越好
get ready to hold your breath for as long as you can.
他吸入了最后一口气
He takes one last breath.
他全神贯注  心如止水
Focused and calm,
潜入了20米深的海底
sulbin descends 20 metres to the sea floor.
他的心跳缓至每分钟30下
His heartbeat slows to around 30 beats per minute.
此深度的压力使他的胸膛受到压迫
The pressure at these depths crushes his chest,
将肺部容量挤至平时的三分之一
squeezing the air in his lungs to one-third of its usual volume,
即使没有负重
Even without weights,
他也无法像在陆地上一样
he's negatively buoyant enough
大步横穿海底  轻松捕猎
to stride across the bottom of the sea as if hunting on land.
现在他血液中的二氧化碳
By now, the carbon dioxide in his blood causes
唤起了一股几乎无法抗拒的对呼吸的渴望
an almost irresistible urge to gasp for air,
但瑟宾必须把精力集中在捕猎上
but Sulbin must keep his mind on the hunt.
1分45秒后
After a minute and three-quarters,
瑟宾发现了一条鱼
Sulbin spots a fish.
瑟宾可以比这次潜得更深
Sulbin can go even deeper than this
并在水下停留5分钟
and stay down for up to five minutes,
但他不需要那样卖弄
but he's not one to show off
毕竟  他已达到了此行的目的
and, after all, he's got what he came for.
靠着一口气在压力下潜水长达两分半之久
Two-and-a-half minutes of hunting under pressure on one breath.
也许人类从海洋哺乳动物进化而来的说法
Perhaps the idea of humans existing as marine mammals
并非那么离谱
is not so far-fetched after all.
通过惊人的努力与适应力
Through amazing adaptability and endeavour,
我们将自身的海洋生存能力推向更高的极限
we've pushed our limits of survival into the ocean
我们在这幽深的世界潜得愈来愈深
and, as we've immersed ourselves deeper in the sea,
它对我们的生活也起了深远的影响
it's had a profound effect on our lives.
但随着我们不断改变着
But as we continue to change
地球大环境的本态
the nature of the greatest environment on our planet,
未来我们将如何适应  还得静观其变
how we'll adapt in the future remains to be seen.
人类星球
镜头背后的故事
在人类星球之海洋节目中
The most technical and demanding shoots
最有技术含量且最耗时耗力的镜头
for the Human Planet: Oceans programme
是那些在水下拍摄的片段
were those that took place underwater.
水下摄像团队已为拍摄菲律宾渔民
The dive camera crew were well prepared
做好了充足的准备
to film fishermen in the Philippines.
但他们对可能面临的危险
But they weren't quite prepared
并无防备
for the dangers they witnessed
也未曾料到友谊的桥梁会从此建起
and the friendships they'd forge.
巴拉望岛  菲律宾
北纬11度11分9秒  西经119度23分44秒
厘米纳科岛是80位深海捕鱼渔民的家乡
Liminangcong is home to the 80
摄像团队将跟随帕阿林潜水员进行拍摄
Pa-aling fishermen that the film crew will follow.
这是西蒙  这是罗杰...
他们将潜到水下
会和你们一同潜水...
并将在水下进行拍摄
两艘渔船上  挤满了80名潜水员
Two fishing boats are crammed with 80 divers,
以及他们的口粮和储备物资
their food and provisions,
这些都是为两周的出海所做的准备
before heading out for two weeks at sea.
在捕鱼区
At the fishing grounds,
西蒙和罗杰在争分夺秒
Simon and Roger are playing catch-up,
因为穿戴潜水装备
as their technical underwater equipment
大大消耗了他们的时间
is slowing them down.
他们已经把绳子扔下去了  都没跟我们说
They've dropped the lines. They didn't even tell us.
罗杰・芒斯
潜水员/摄像师
船长今天好像要大干一番
The captain seems to be on a mission
一副志在必得的样子
to prove something today
所以我们得加快速度了
so we've got to go fast.
水下拍摄危机四伏
Underwater filming is risky,
但与用压缩机潜水的人们每天所遭遇的相比
but these risks are nothing compared to those faced daily
这些真是小巫见大巫
by the compressor divers.
压缩机潜水是极端危险的谋生手段
Compressor diving is a dangerous way to make a living.
这种常被柴油污染的空气
Air, often tainted with diesel,
通过细塑料管
is pumped through thin plastic tubes
直接被潜水员吸入体内
right down to the divers.
迪奥尼斯奥・杰宁・马丁尼托
压缩机潜水员
64岁的杰宁是船上一位经验丰富的潜水员
At 64, Joning is one of the veterans on the boat,
他深知压缩机潜水的残酷
and knows the harsh realities of compressor diving.
我当压缩机潜水员已经有30年了
我15岁时...
就开始下海工作
大多数潜水员年轻体壮
Most of the divers are young and fit,
他们也必须如此
and they need to be.
这是个极其耗费体力的工作
It's physically demanding work,
潜水员完全依靠压缩机
and the men are totally reliant on the compressor
维持呼吸
to keep them breathing.
如果你靠压缩机潜到海底
...机器功率稍有减弱
你就会缺氧...
...造成胸腔受损
说实话
To use, basically, what's essentially
用浇花园的水管下潜25米
a garden hose down at 25 metres,
还要把空气压缩进嘴里  真是太疯狂了
to pump air into your mouth, is just mad.
对这些渔民来说最大的危险
The biggest danger for these fishermen is known as
就是减压病  俗称"潜水病"
decompression sickness, or "the bends".
当潜水员长时间深潜
The bends can happen when divers have been down deep
而又出水过快时
for a long time,
就会得减压病
and then come up too quickly to the surface.
氮气会进入潜水员体内
Nitrogen is absorbed into the body
当他们上浮时
and, as the divers rise up,
各个关节处会形成气泡
bubbles are formed that can lodge in the joints,
造成剧烈的疼痛
causing intense pain.
有两名潜水员在这次深潜中深受其害
Two guys are in real trouble on this deep dive.
马丁  一名年轻的潜水员  疼痛难忍
Martin, a young diver, is in such pain
他朋友试图通过按摩来减轻他的病痛
that his friend tries to relieve it by massaging him.
等到浮出水面  大家都看得出
Once on the surface, it's obvious to everyone
马丁的情况仍未好转
that Martin is still in trouble.
如若不治疗
If not treated,
减压病会导致终生残疾  甚至是死亡
the bends can lead to permanent injuries and even death.
同时  另一名潜水员迈克尔
Meanwhile, the second diver,
同样遇到了麻烦
Michael, is also having problems.
看起来有两个人出现了减压症
It seems like two men just came up with the bends.
汤姆・休・琼斯
《人类星球》制片人
他们为了捕到更多的鱼
They went pretty deep on this dive,
潜得太深了
trying to get more fish.
我们已经把他们安置到船上
But we've taken them onto our boat
对他们实施急救
to get some medical attention
希望他们都没事
so, hopefully, they're all right.
西蒙设法用船员急救用品
Simon tries to relieve their symptoms
帮助缓解他们的症状
with the crew's first aid supplies.
再吸一次氧
One more.
迈克尔已经吸了15分钟氧气
Michael's had 15 minutes on oxygen.
现在让马丁再吸15分钟氧气
Now put Martin onto another set of 15 minutes.
西蒙・恩德比
潜水员/摄影师
这是
This is the...you know,
我们目前能提供的
the rudimentary decompression first aid
最基本的减压急救措施  让他们吸氧
we can give them at the moment- give them oxygen,
给他们补水并让他们保暖
give them water to rehydrate and keep them warm.
他们都表示
Both of them are saying that
症状有所减轻
their symptoms are decreasing
他们看起来比半小时前
and they are looking a lot more happy
精神了一些
than they did about half an hour ago.
他让他们吸更多氧气
He gives them oxygen,
以帮助降低体内氮气含量
which helps reduce the nitrogen in their bodies
减轻他们的痛苦
and relieves their pain,
但即使是这种最基本的潜水急救措施
but even this most basic of diving first aid
对于帕阿林渔民来说  都是可望而不可及的
is not normally available to the Pa-aling fishermen.
不疼了吗
No pain?
在菲律宾  渔民属于低收入人群
This isn't surprising as the fishermen in the Philippines
一周仅有25美元的收入
belong to the lowest wage earners in the country,
这样的情况不足为奇
earning about 25 US dollars for a week's work.
然而  对于许多像杰宁家一样的渔民来说
However, for many, like Joning and his family,
这是生活唯一的出路
this is their whole way of life.
我的三个儿子和一个孙子
参加了这次出海任务
我经常提醒儿子们要小心...
大儿子要依靠压缩机...
在36米的深度
待上4个小时
当他上浮时...
气泡袭击了他的身体
他儿子得了减压病
His son had got the bends,
现在要借助拐杖行走
and now has to use crutches.
但这并不是唯一一次
But this isn't the only time
压缩机潜水的魔爪
the dangers of compressor diving
伸向杰宁一家
have hit Joning's family.
我二儿子在一次潜水后瘫痪了
他无法接受这个事实...
他很想好起来
我费尽心力
想找个人给他治病...
...但缺钱
将近一年后...
我们也无能为力了...
我的儿子  悲痛欲绝之际...
决定上吊自杀
节哀顺变
I'm very sorry about that.
太悲剧了
Yeah. That's terrible.
这让你...很难过吧
That's really...That's really sad, isn't it?
是的
It is.
与压缩机潜水员
Having spent a week
工作生活了一周之后
living and working with the compressor divers,
西蒙和罗杰与这些渔民成为了朋友
Simon and Roger have become very close to the fishermen.
为了充分了解他们的生活方式
To fully understand their way of life,
西蒙要亲身体验
Simon needed to experience first-hand
做一名压缩机潜水员
what it's like to be a compressor diver.
杰宁很乐意带他进行一次浅层潜水
So Joning is keen to take him on a shallow dive.
我看他们这么做过  看起来很容易
I've seen the boys do it. They've made it look easy.
但已经有好几个人
But we've had several guys that
出现了减压病的症状
have gone down with symptoms of the bends.
不得不承认
I've got to admit that
我有点虚
I'm feeling a little bit apprehensive.
西蒙有16年的水肺潜水经验
Simon has scuba-dived for 16 years
超过3000次的潜水经历
and has logged over 3,000 dives,
而这却是最回归原始的一次潜水
but this is diving at its most basic.
一分钟左右  我被送下水
About the first minute, I got sent out,
说真的  我有点吓呆了
I was, er...a little bit petrified, actually.
这玩意太猛了
This is a violent thing.
空气直接往喉咙里灌
It's just punching air down your throat.
真是太疯狂了
It's quite mad.
我花了一分钟来控制身体平衡
It took me a minute to kind of get myself under control
一旦你摸到了诀窍
and then once you've got the hang of it,
并充分信赖起这套装置
and once you believe in it and trust in it,
就能继续游了
then you can swim on.
有好几次送气管从嘴里掉出来时
There were a couple of times when I lost it, though.
我一阵挣扎
I was flailing around everywhere.
想把它抓住塞回嘴里
I was trying to find it again and get it back in.
虽然杰宁一直密切关注着我
But Joning was keeping a good eye on me,
其他人也是如此
and the rest of the guys were as well,
但我可不希望整个捕鱼过程中
but I wouldn't want to do that
都得这样潜水
for a whole fish-catching session
这一点是肯定的
that's for sure.
潜水员之间建立了深厚的友谊
A strong camaraderie between the divers has been forged.
摄像团队抓拍到了这感人至深的一幕
The film crew have captured a dramatic sequence,
渔民们满载而归
and the fishermen head home happy,
可以高兴地回家了
with a boatload of fish to sell.
当你和大家打成一片时...
你会觉得船上的生活格外美妙
如果收获颇丰...
大家都会很开心
杰宁和船上一行人
Joning and everyone on board
又完成了一次深海捕鱼行动
have finished another Pa-aling fishing trip,
大家都能开心平安地回到家人身边了
and all can return safe and sound to their families.